Guide to the Caspar F. Goodrich Collection 1862-1933 MS 439.21
New-York Historical Society
Caspar F. Goodrich Collection
1862-1933
New-York Historical Society
MS 439.21
1.3 Linear feet (3 boxes, 1 volume)
The collection includes official correspondence, notes and texts of lectures Admiral Goodrich delivered while an instructor at the Naval War College, other writings including the edited manuscript of his memoirs, extracts from the diary of his grandfather Captain James Goodrich, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings on the Spanish-American War.
Provenance
Donated to the New-York Historical Society in 1936 by the Naval History Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1847 Caspar Frederick Goodrich born Philadelphia, January 7
1861-1864 Attends US Naval Academy, graduating first in his class
1864-1865 Assigned to New York Navy Yard
1865-1868 With European squadron aboard Colorado and Frolic
1868 Promoted to Lieutenant Commander
1868-1871 Aboard Portsmouth, South Atlantic Squadron
1871-1874 At US Naval Academy; teaches physics and chemistry in 1871. Helps to found U.S. Naval Institute
1876 Daughter Eleanor born
1881 Son Caspar born, Florence, Italy
1881-1884 Aboard Lancaster, flagship for European Squadron
1882-1885 Inspector of ordnance, Washington Navy Yard
1883 Publishes "Report of the British naval and military operations in Egypt, 1882"
1886-1890 Officer in charge, Torpedo Station, Newport, RI
1889 Serves as President, Naval War College, Portsmouth, RI
1891 Torpedo Board formed to research uses of torpedoes in naval operations
1891-1896 Commands sail training ships Jamestown and Constellation, and gunboat Concord
1897 Promoted to captain
1897-1898 Serves as President, Naval War College, Portsmouth, RI
1898 Originates Coastal Signal Service (designed to warn shoreline populace of an impending coastal attack by foreign ships) and serves as its Director
1898 Commands St. Louis and Newark during the Spanish-American War, receiving the surrender of Manzanillo, Cuba, 12 August
1899-1900 Commands Iowa in Pacific Squadron
1900 Publishes "The naval side of the revolutionary war"
1900-1901 Lecturer, Naval War College, Portsmouth, RI
1901-1904 Commandant, Philadelphia Navy Yard
1904 Promoted to rear admiral
1904-1906 Named commander in chief, Pacific Fleet
1904-1909 Serves as President, U.S. Naval Institute
1907 Lieutenant Caspar Goodrich killed aboard USS Georgia, 15 July
1907-1909 Commandant, New York Navy Yard
1909 Retires from active duty
1914-1916 President, Naval History Society
1918 Recalled to active duty as Commander, Naval Training Unit, Princeton Graduate College
1918-1919: Officer in charge of Pay Officers Material School, Princeton Graduate College
1924 Writes memoir "Rope yarns from the old navy"
1925 Dies, Princeton, New Jersey
1931 Naval History Society publishes "Rope yarns from the old navy," edited by James Barnes, as eleventh volume of its publications
1933 Mrs. Goodrich donates the manuscript of "Rope yarns" to the Naval History Society
1936 Eleanor Goodrich (Mrs. C.T Davis) donates Goodrich collection to the Naval History Society
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes official correspondence, notes and texts of lectures Admiral Goodrich delivered while a lecturer at the Naval War College, other writings including the edited manuscript of his memoirs, and extracts from the diary of his grandfather, Captain James Goodrich.
The Goodrich Collection forms Series 21 of the Naval History Society Collection, comprising 53 individual collections named for famous naval figures and ships, as well as the records of the Naval History Society itself, and donated to the New-York Historical Society by the Naval History Society in 1925.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series:
Missing Title
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Naval War College lectures and lecture notes
Series III. Writings
Series IV. James Goodrich journal transcripts
Series V. Bound volumes
Coast Defenses; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (documents); Maps.; Naval battles.; Naval education -- United States.; Naval tactics; Navy-yards and naval stations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Navy-yards and naval stations -- Pennsylvania.; Orders (military records).; Photographic prints.; Scrapbooks.; Transcripts.; Goodrich, Caspar Frederick, 1847-1925; Naval War College (U.S.); United States Naval Institute; Colorado (Frigate); Kearsarge (Sloop); Princeton University -- History -- 20th century; United States. Navy -- Officers -- Education; United States. Navy -- History -- Spanish American War, 1898
- Series I: Correspondence (1871-1918)
  Scope and Contents note
  The series consists mainly of official correspondence received, including orders to report to ships, permissions for leave, administration of the Torpedo Board, service on various courts martial, and assignments to lecture at the Naval War College. The letters sent are mostly typescript carbons with some letterpress copies, and include official reports filed on operations and cruises, providing details of the responsibilities of a ship's commander in this period. John Meigs's January 1909 letters discuss the formation of a naval historical society and in that year John Sanford Barnes sends draft bylaws of the Naval Historical Society, comparing it to Britain's Naval Records Society. The last document was found in the original Correspondence box and is not in Goodrich's handwriting; it may have been written by New-York Historical Society librarian Dorothy Barck.
  - Letters sent, 1871-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters sent: Draft to Ben Lamberton, 1895 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters received, 1863 -1878 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters received, 1881 -1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters received, 1885 - 1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters received, 1888 - 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters received, 1890 - 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters received, 1894 - 1895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters received, 1896 - 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters received, 1903 - 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters received, 1909, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed enclosure: H.R. 8476, Committee on Naval Affairs, U.S. House of Representatives, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Note on post-war planning, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. Naval War College lectures and lecture notes (1862-1904)
  The subseries includes notes, handwritten drafts, and final versions (mostly carbon typescripts) of lectures Goodrich presented at the Naval War College, as well as notes on other topics. Also included are a newspaper clipping and a list of personal items, perhaps from the Goodrich residence, found with the lecture materials. "The Problem of 96" is one of the annual examinations by College cadets of a challenge in coastal defense: the 1896 one looked at a specific part of nearby Narragansett Bay. This is an early precursor of the theoretical "war games" the College famously initiated.
  The numbered lectures were delivered in order as part of a series on famous international naval encounters, from the Battle of Sluys in 1340 to Drake's destruction of King Phillip's fleet in Cadiz Harbor in 1587, Napoleon's Nile Campaign of 1798, and the 1827 Battle of Navarino during the Greek War of Independence. These form the backdrop for Goodrich's final multipart lecture on Dewey's engagement in Manila during the Spanish-American War, which had occurred only three years before these lectures. It is unclear if the material on the Army's landing in Cuba formed part of this presentation.
  Arrangement
  The lecture notes are arranged chronologically and the numbered lectures in order as noted on them and their original packaging. Some lectures' accompanying graphic materials (maps and photoreproductions probably used in the preparation of lantern slides) were pinned to the lecture text; these have been separated, numbered by page on which they appeared, and housed by lecture. The notes' original envelopes are in separate folders; they may date any time from the lectures in 1901 to the collection's donation to the Naval History Society in 1933.
  - Extract from "Fortifications and Sea Coast Defenses," Congressional Committee on Military Affairs, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lists of personal items, probably 1890s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Problem of 96: Eggemoggin Reach; copy of Admiral Mahan letter to Taylor on the subject, 1895 July 19, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clipping on privateering, 1896 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letter on armored cruisers from Admiral W.S. Schley, 1896 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Naval War College documents: Elements of a "War Chart and Defense Plan"; definition of art of war; document on international law, 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter defining Mediterranean compass variations 1798; notes on Egyptian campaign of 1798, 1901 Jan 22, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - First lecture: Battle of Sluys. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - First lecture: Battle of Sluys. Photoreproductions, maps, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Second lecture: Singeing the King of Spain's Beard: Cadiz, 1587. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Second lecture: Singeing the King of Spain's Beard: Cadiz, 1587. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Maps and photoreproductions., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fourth lecture: Blake's last fight - Santa Cruz de Teneriffe, April 20, 1627. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fifth lecture: The Nile Campaign I. The Pursuit. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Maps and reproductions, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Seventh lecture: The Battle of Navarino. Draft., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Dewey at Manila: Notes, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dewey at Manila: I. Introduction. II. Strained Relations. III. Dewey's Objectives. IV. Authorities. V. American Preparations, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dewey at Manila: VI. The Opposing Forces. VII. Spanish Preparations. VIII. Spanish Accounts of the Battle, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Dewey at Manila: IX. American Accounts of the Battle. X. The Finish, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The landing of the army in Cuba, circa 1901 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Assorted lecture notes. Envelope, 1904 (Box OS 1, Folder 8)
  - Second lecture. Singeing of the King of Spain's Beard. Envelope, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 9)
  - Seventh lecture. The Battle of Navarino. Envelope, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 10)
  - Seventh lecture. The Battle of Navarino. Map blueprints, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 11)
  - Sixth lecture. Battle of the Nile. Envelopes, Undated (Box OS 3, Folder 1)
- Series III. Writings (1901-1933)
  The subseries includes notes and final versions of Goodrich's writings, apart from the lectures he delivered at the Naval War College, including various topics in naval warfare, an address on establishing a naval training facility in San Diego, and his 1924 memoirs. The latter includes a typescript with handwritten emendations probably by James Barnes, who edited the work for publication by the Naval History Society ("Rope yarns from the old navy," published by J.J. Little & Ives Co., as the eleventh volume of the Society's publications), and a final clean version incorporating those changes. The memoirs are an affectionate look at his early service in the Navy, which he describes as "coincident with the great changes from sail to steam; from wooden frigates to steel dreadnoughts; from smooth bore muzzle loaders to breech loading rifled cannon; from man power to electricity."
  - Logistics, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Coast defense, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Label from wrapper for writings on coast defense and logistics, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Navigation, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Interior water communication, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scouting for the U.S.S. Tacony, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dutch - French - English Wars of the 17th Century, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Extracts from G.B. Mundy's 1830 Biography of Admiral Rodney, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Confidential report of Gunnery Information Obtained During a Visit to England - British Battle Practice", 1905 June (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Comments to San Diego Chamber of Commerce about establishing a naval training station, circa 1916 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - In memoriam: Tribute to Stephen Bleecker Luce, published by the Naval History Society, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Cover page, foreword, comments, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": I. How I Entered the Navy. II. At the Naval Academy During the Civil War. III. Some Experiences as a Midshipman, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": IV. Goldsborough. V. My First Foreign Port. VI. Mediterranean Cruise, Concluded. VII. With Farragut, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": VIII. In the South Atlantic, 1869-1871. IX. A Remote Island Community. X. St. Paul de Loando - St. Helena - Ascension. XI. In Asiatic Waters, 1875-1878, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": XII. Another European Cruise. XIII. Another European Cruise (Concluded). XIV. The Last of My Sailing Ships: 1. The Jamestown., 1924 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": XV. 2. The Constellation. XVI. Bluejackets of the Old Navy, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Complete revised typescript, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Typescript box, presented to the Naval History Society March 29, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series IV. James Goodrich journal transcripts (undated)
  The subseries consists of undated notes in Goodrich's hand, and a typed transcript, from the logs of Captain James Goodrich (dated 1796-1853) aboard various vessels, including Confederacy. These may be related to the publication in Journal of American History (IV, II, pp. 273-280, 1910) of "First Commerce Under American Flag," by William Goodrich (grandson of James and brother of Caspar F.), which documents James Goodrich's claims against the French government for restitution of goods seized on a voyage.
  - "Notes from the log of the Confederacy from London to Madeira to China (in which James Goodrich sailed), 1796 Jan 10 - 1797 June 9, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Miscellaneous abstracts from journal on board the ship Fame etc. of Capt. James Goodrich, London to New Orleans", 1800-1801, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Random notes from the journals of Captain James W. Goodrich", 1823 - 1853, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Typed transcript from James Goodrich logs: Conditions in Whampoa, China (probably aboard Galaxy), circa 1835, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Subseries V. Bound volumes
  The subseries consists of a scrapbook of newspaper clippings on the Spanish-American War.
  - Scrapbook of clippings on the Spanish-American War, 1898 (Volume 1)